So today we are going to make a Hendars
style white chocolate ice cream to go
with the macarons that we made last
week. But before we start, let's look at
what makes Hagen different.
[Music]
Out of all the storebought ice creams,
Hagen is probably my favorite. Um
Hagen's Belgian chocolate is hands down
my favorite storebought ice cream. Um I
haven't tried them all. There are
millions of them. So, you know, it is
what it is. I'm sure there's other ones
out there that I like, but Häen's on
average is about 12 to 13 1/2% fat, but
also is about 20 to 22% sugar. And that
can be from a standard vanilla all the
way up to something like this, which is
12% fat, 23% sugar. That does include
the add-ins. So we have to consider that
when you look at things like the vanilla
then the average sugar content and it
does differ from country to country but
the average sugar content is around 20
to 22%.
Now they do that because they don't have
any other type of ingredients in there.
It's pretty standard ingredients goes
into henars. They say it's cream milk,
eggs and sugar. It it's not. It's the
way they word it. It's a sales pitch.
They actually use condensed milk. But as
it's just a milk product with sugar,
it's encompassed under those ones that
they describe. So they use milk, cream,
condensed milk, sugar, and then for
vanilla, they use the vanilla extract
and or vanilla bean. U sometimes in
Mexico they use vanilla bean paste. In
the US, they use both vanilla extract
and vanilla paste. In the UK, I think
they just use vanilla extract. So it
it's kind of different everywhere. And
that's how Hagenars advertises their ice
cream. Obviously, today I'm going to use
the macarons that I made last week. Uh I
know that video wasn't amazingly popular
cuz it's not ice cream, but here we go.
Um let's look at the nutrition label for
the chocolate version of that macaron
ice cream. And this is from St. Louis in
the UK. Everything is laid out by 100 g
amounts. And then it gives you an exact
percentage of how much each ingredient
is. So, as we can see from here, we have
16.9%
fat and down there we have 19.9. So,
basically 20% sugar with a little bit of
protein and salt. And actually, I think
this is the vanilla rather than the
chocolate. Looking at the ingredients
for the same vanilla, we've got fresh
cream, condensed skimmed, milk, sugar,
water, egg yolk, natural vanilla
flavoring. So, when we break those
ingredients down, we have fresh cream,
and they state 39% fresh cream, which
that that's pretty damn high. Um, I I
would want to try and create this
exactly one day, and I I'm I will one
day, but then we got our condensed skim
milk as our number one ingredient. And
our condensed skim milk is literally
just condensed milk with sugar added.
So, you can see how they have linked
condensed skim milk, sugar, water.
Again, water is added to the mix to
balance it out to the numbers that they
require with egg yolk and then natural
vanilla flavoring. Natural vanilla
flavoring could be vanilla, which is the
super cheap flavor. And again, it's a
saint. So, this is a UK website. Their
Hagen vanilla over there has no bean
seeds in it. So, it's, you know, it's
that's why I'm not a big fan of that
vanilla ice cream. But with that aside,
we can see that there's a pattern with
Hand does ice cream with the same kind
of high fat levels and high sugar
levels. The sugar levels are actually in
line with standard gelato um which is
much higher sugar than standard US ice
cream. US ice cream is higher in fat and
lower in sugar relatively speaking and
gelato so Italian gelato is lower in fat
and higher in sugar. But when we open up
the macaron ice cream that they had
this, ignore the Belgian chocolate pint.
That's an advert for the next flavor. We
can actually see that the sugar level is
24.8.
And I'll highlight it here for you. The
sugar level 24.8%.
Fat levels are also high at 18.3%.
Again, I'll highlight it here. So,
really high. Now, I'm I I don't feel
comfortable doing 18 and a half% fat
content over here because it just it
doesn't end well. You get fatty kind of
textures. In the UK with double cream,
you can. Uh Japanese cream, you can. I
can't speak for all of Europe because,
you know, cream is different in every
country, but French cream is excellent.
German cream is also excellent. Austrian
cream is delicious. You know, Jersey
cream, oh, it's great. And you can go
much higher in fat content with those
than you can with kind of this stuff,
you know.
So, with that aside, I've brought the
fat level down to as high as I'm
comfortable to go here. And that is
about 16%. Sugar levels, I've had to
bring those down. Getting up to 20 to
24% sugar is just insane. So, we've
brought that down and balanced it so
that we've got a decent serving
temperature of -15. So, centigrade that
is. So, it's still pretty high in sugar,
but this is how we recreate hagenars at
home. There's no stabilizers in this cuz
there's no stabilizers in hagenars. So,
what are we going to need? We're going
to need 521 g of milk, 695 g of whipping
cream, 33% heavy cream is fine.
163 g of sugar, 86 g of egg yolk, 347 g
of condensed milk, which is 1 300 ml
can,
and 186 g of white chocolate. So, uh, I
had someone in the US say that my can of
condensed milk was wrong. Um, and that
all condensed milk cans are bigger and
that is just a letter of rubbish. In the
US, you can get bigger cans of condensed
milk. Here in Canada, they are all this
size. 300 milliliters. Same in the UK,
same in Europe. So, can't speak for
Mexico,
but in the US, it's a 300 ml can, like
every other country. That's what you're
going to need. In here, I have my milk,
which is 521 g. We're going to add in
our sugar, our cream, 695 g. So, our
entire can, 300 ml of condensed milk.
Now we're going to do the egg yolks. I'm
going to separate these eggs because I'm
going to use the whites to make some
more macarons.
So 86 gram of egg yolks.
So for me that was five large eggs. They
are going to go straight into there. And
now we are simply going to get this on
the hob and slowly mix it up. Stir it
together. As the temperature gets warm,
we're going to add in our chocolate. So,
let's get that started. You have to
continually stir these henars egg yolk
bases because we don't want those egg
yolks to stick to the bottom of the pan
and go weird hard and they will also
turn your entire mix into scrambled egg
if you're not careful. So, continually
stirring is important and as the
temperature increases, it's even more
important. So you need to watch egg
based ice cream carefully. So now that
we're coming up to temperature, we're
going to add in our white chocolate.
Now with the white chocolate here in, we
are just going to gently keep stirring
that until we bring that together. Egg
yolks, we need to bring those up to just
70 centrade, which is this in
Fahrenheit. Any higher, and we're going
to risk burning those and scrambling our
base. So that's the temperature we're
aiming for here. Now that we're up to
temperature, we're going to get this
into a bowl.
So, we're going to chill this in the
refrigerator. Uh, it's white chocolate.
So, white chocolate when chilled in an
ice cream base will give you a layer on
the top. And I'll show you that when I
take it out of the fridge. So, when your
mix comes out of the fridge, you can see
there's just a thin layer on top. That
will happen with white chocolate. Just
get it completely mixed back in. A good
whisk will sort that and fully
incorporate it back in. Get it in your
pre-chilled machine and try not to
overflow the machine like I did. Whilst
it's churning, we're going to chop up
our macarons. These are the really nice
ones. As you can see, there's one on the
left that was the bad, one on the right
that was the good. And we're going to
chop these up into quarters because now
that our ice cream is ready, we're going
to load these in a few per layer and
dish up after being in the freezer for
four or five hours. It's a really good
scoop. Lovely pieces of macaron showing
through. Beautiful texture ice cream.
Look at that. Gorgeous. Let's try it. I
tried the Hagen's macaron ice cream last
year or the year before or whatever it
was. The chocolate version. It was
really, really good. There are four
flavors. At the time that it was
available to me, there are only two
flavors, chocolate and it appears
raspberry, strawberry,
but now there's I think a yuzu and a
blueberry. I don't know if they're
available everywhere. Haven't seen them
over here with the macarons last week.
That turned out really good. It was only
a natural progression to do something
with them.
Let's see how this turned out.
Delicious. The ice cream is beautiful.
It's a really strange thing to consider
such a big brand such as Arandars using
condensed milk, but they absolutely do.
Uh, I'm pretty sure they use it in every
single one of their ice creams as well.
So, don't be surprised. The macarons.
This was the first one, the first batch,
my first attempt, and this was my second
attempt. Just so you can see
the difference here. Not the right
texture when made, which means
they were kind of hollow in the top.
They still taste great, but these are
the ones. Perfect. Crispy texture, chewy
on the inside,
delicious. I mean, I'll still eat this
one every day of the week. So, with that
white chocolate ganache inside the
macarons, it was only an obvious choice
really to to make the white chocolate
hagen ice cream. It's a great base for
any kind of addings that you want.
Anyway, thanks very much for watching.
Don't forget to like and subscribe. I'll
see you next week.
[Music]